Guide to the Stanford University, Student Affairs Committee, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Student Affairs Committee, records
1895-1924
1901-1917
SC0016
Stanford University. Student Affairs Committee.
1.25 Linear feet
Minutes, correspondence, reports, and other records pertaining to student discipline.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, date unknown.
Information about Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Historical Note
The Student Affairs Committee, a faculty committee of the Academic Council, was responsible for student discipline during the early years of Stanford's history. Rufus Lot Green was chairman from 1901 to 1906, succeeded by William F. Durand who served from September 1906 to January 1908. Prof. A. B. Clark was chairman from February 1908 until the fall of 1914 when Frederic C. Woodward was appointed chairman.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Records in this collection include minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, and notices, 1895-1924 (bulk 1901-1917). Many of the records pertain to the problem of student drinking, both on and off campus, especially an incident in 1908 that led to a larger student demonstration. Other subjects include hazing, in particular the practice of "tubbing" at Encina Hall, cheating, non-payment of bills by individuals and organizations, fraternity matters, permission for social events, and objectionable editorials/articles on the part of student authors/editors.
Access Terms
Adams, Bristow; Clark, Arthur Bridgman, 1866-1948; Durand, William Frederick, 1859-1958; Green, Rufus Lot, 1862-1932.; Woodward, Frederick Campbell, 1874-; Cheating (Education).; College discipline--United States.; College students--Alcohol use--United States.; College students--United States--Conduct of life.; Hazing--United States.
Collection Contents
- Minutes and documents, 1906-07 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Minutes and documents, 1908 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes reports on "The customs as to the use of liquor in Stanford University" and "The parade or demonstration of March 12th."
- Minutes and documents, 1908 Feb-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes "Report of [Alumni] Committee, Findings of Fact and Conclusions"
- Minutes and documents, 1908 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Minutes and documents, 1908 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Minutes and documents, 1909 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Minutes and documents, 1909 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Minutes and documents, 1910 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Minutes and documents, 1910 Aug-Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Minutes and documents, 1910 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Minutes and documents, 1911 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Minutes and documents, 1911 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes "Report of the Committee on Student Affairs for the Academic Year 1910-1911" with much information on the practice of "tubbing" in Encina Hall.
- Minutes and documents, 1911 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Minutes and documents, 1912 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Minutes and documents, 1912 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Minutes and documents, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Includes many documents from the Men's and Women's Student Councils
- Minutes and documents, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes "Circular of Information for Members of the Student Conferences and of the Faculty Committee on Student Affairs" and "Report of the President of the University Conference for the Year 1913-14"
- Minutes and documents, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Minutes and documents, 1916 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Minutes and documents, 1916 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes committee reports on cheating at Stanford 1915-1916, "Student Views on Cheating, 1915-1916," and "Report of Women's Student Council and of Women's Student Conference for 1915-16"
- Minutes and documents (A.B. Clark's copy), 1908-09 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Minutes and documents (A.B. Clark's copy), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Minutes and documents (A.B. Clark's copy), 1911-14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Suspensions and dismissals, 1894-1899 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Suspensions and dismissals, 1900-05 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Suspensions and dismissals, 1906-09 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Suspensions and dismissals, 1910-13 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Suspensions and dismissals, 1914-17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous memoranda, 1918, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases, 1898-1901 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases, 1905 Mar-Aug (Box 2, Folder 15)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases, 1905 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases (#1), 1906 Jan (Box 2, Folder 17)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases (#2), 1906 Jan (Box 2, Folder 18)
- R. L. Green's file: conduct cases, 1906 Mar-Dec (Box 3, Folder 1)
- R. L. Green's file: Encina disturbances, 1905 May (Box 3, Folder 2)
- R. L. Green's file: Encina disturbances, 1905 Sep (Box 3, Folder 3)
- R. L. Green's file: Encina disturbances, 1905 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 4)
- R. L. Green's file: Encina disturbances, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- R. L. Green's file: Liquor troubles (outside Encina), 1905-06 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- R. L. Green's file: Miscellaneous, 1895-1905 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes letter and statement by Bristow Adams re article in Chaparral, Apr. 1901
- R. L. Green's file: Student affairs, 1899-1905 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Includes copy of "Encina Hall Rules and Regulations"
- R. L. Green's file: Unpaid student bills, 1896-1905 (Box 3, Folder 9)